Hello!
In today's episode of Bug Bounty Reports Explained,
I will show you a critical vulnerability
in GitLab that involves four steps to get an XSS.
And it was great but even better is the way it was escalated
into reading arbitrary files from the server, including secrets.yaml.
The vulnerability was discovered by William Bowlling,
who tends to find awesome vulnerabilities
and has already been on this channel twice.
Link to the original report is in the description.
Enjoy!
Recently on Twitter, I posted
how much money I made from AdSense in a year.
It wasn't much,
but luckily there are companies like Detectify who support
content creators, and I'm partnering with them for a whole month.
Unlike other tools out there,
Detectify does both asset discovery by, for example,
crawling your DNS, and then it also does vulnerability scanning.
Of course, it can do simple things from OWASP TOP 10
like CORS misconfiguration or check vulnerable versions.
But the cool part is
they are working with a private community of ethical hackers
who submit payloads or POCs with automatable web vulnerabilities.
After the review, Detective runs the attack on all their customers,
and every time there is a hit, the hacker gets a bounty.
So if you are a defender and you want to protect your apps,
check out free two week trial at detectify.com/BBRE.
And remember, go hack yourself.
GitLab design management allows you to upload
images like wireframes or mockups to a GitLab issue.
The goal is to store them in one place, but for us
it's enough to know that it allows attaching images to issues.
And text in issues supports markdown.
It's a very light markup language for creating formatted text.
Among others, it supports links.
This is the syntax you use, which is then transformed to this HTML code.
And the links that were leading to an image from a design
were treated differently.
The issue ID and the filename were shown as the link's content.
So GitLab needed to know if your link leads to a design or not.
For that, regular expressions were used.
First, the server checked
if the path was linking to a design using path_segment regex.
Nothing out of line was noticed here.
But then it extracted the filename using this regex.
It means any character that is not a forward slash or whitespace,
followed by a dot and followed by an extension.
It means that a quote before the dot is perfectly fine.
And your link would eventually be present
in the href attribute of an a tag.
So you could use this double quote to escape this attribute.
But for that to actually work,
you would have to upload a file with such filename first.
It was a problem because the sanitizer
would not allow double quotes in the filename.
However, when using this strange content disposition header,
you bypassed the workhorse and bypassed the sanitizer.
This unusual syntax means
that the filename is written using ASCII-8bit charset.
The empty value between quotes is a place for a language
which is apparently not required.
Then,
there is the filename, which in this case is just a standard string.
What probably happens, is the sanitizer
can't parse this filename or does not support this charset
so it just ignores it,
thus allowing files with quotes in their names.
How do you then execute the
XSS if you can't use spaces or forward slashes?
You could use
a new tag without any attributes
but you would be blocked by content security policy.
But turns out that when you have multiple attributes,
you don't need a space or a slash to separate them.
If you use quotes, you can use one attribute next to another.
This way, you can inject arbitrary attributes to this a tag.
How to now turn it into an XSS?
Injecting any event handlers will not work because it would
also be blocked by content security policy.
But turns out that ReferenceRedactor has a functionality
that might be just the right fit for the job.
It takes the value of data-original attribute
and puts it inside the innerHTML of a link.
So you create a design with such payload.
It closes the original quote that will be after the link,
then it adds another attribute class="gfm" which just makes sure
that we will go through desired, vulnerable functions.
Next, it adds yet another attribute.
This time it's unclosed with only one single quote.
Thanks to leaving this attribute unclosed,
we will be able to put our payload in the issue's comment
instead of putting the whole payload in the filename.
Then, you add this as the issue's comment,
referencing your file with malicious name.
Markdown does allow you to use HTML,
but of course, easy XSS will not work here.
As the content of the link, you add this,
with one single quote at the beginning
and then arbitrary attributes that you want to inject.
As you are no longer in the filename, you can now use spaces.
So you use the
data-original attribute with arbitrary HTML code.
We'll come back in a second to this specific payload.
You also need to add a few more attributes in order to avoid exceptions.
Then, the first transformation puts your content
as an actual attribute of the a tag and then ReferenceRedactor
takes the value of this data-original
and puts the contents into an actual content of the tag.
This way, you can inject arbitrary HTML to GitLab issue.
But the next problem is content security policy.
It blocks executing an inline script
so you can't use a script tag with any JavaScript code.
However, CSP allows content from
apis.google.com domain and this one serves JSONP endpoint.
It works the way that in the URL, you tell Google server
what contents you want to be present in the JavaScript file.
As the callback parameter, you give the function name
and as the q parameter, you give the first argument.
So when calling it with this URL,
it will call setTimeout function and execute the alert.
So that's the full cross-site scripting.
It's crazy how many things had to align for this to be possible.
Regular expression for the file name, then bypassing the validator,
using data-original attribute and finally, bypassing the CSP.
But the best thing is that it's not even the end
because William escalated this XSS even further
because five days later, he submitted another comment in this report.
In GitLab,
there is a functionality to send e-mail notifications about issues.
And their content is present in such messages.
And premailer-rails will try to fetch all the external CSS files
and put them inside this email
so that the mail doesn't require external content.
So for each stylesheet, it will take the href attribute
and try to fetch it on the server before sending an email.
It can be an HTTP link, but it can also lead to a local file.
In the first comment,
William presented a way to leak a last line of any file,
but in another one he showed a way to leak whole contents.
If you use such tag,
the server will try to embed contents of
/etc/passwd file in the CSS.
However, this one alone would break the CSS syntax.
In order to avoid it, fetch the opening
and closing of this expression from your own server.
The content in between will be the leaked part from the server,
and it will not cause any exceptions.
This way, you can read any file present
on the server, including files like
secrets.yaml or gitlab.yaml.
You can also execute an
SSRF attack this way.
The report has been awarded $16,000,
which is the middle of the range for critical bug in GitLab.
And that's it.
I absolutely loved this report!
If you enjoyed the video, leave a like and check out
other William's reports that I covered on my channel
about complex bugs with critical impact in GitHub and GitLab.
Also, if you're a defender, check out the free trial of Detectify. For now, thank you for watching and goodbye!